Matthew T. Bowen

Profile

Hello! I'm Matt, a student at the Royal Military College of Canada, where I am pursuing a Master's of Science degree in Physics & Space Science with a research focus on remote sensing. I graduated from Queen's University in 2018 with a Bachelor's of Science (Honours) in Physics and Computing Science. In addition to my studies, I have a background in electrical engineering through various jobs and volunteer positions. Currently, I am the Chief Technical Officer for the Queen's Space Engineering Team's Satellite Project, as well as a Junior Web Developer at Docupet Inc., a Kingston based technology startup.

Education

Royal Military College of Canada

Kingston, ON

Master's of Science - Physics and Space Science

2018 - 2020

NSERC CREATE International Space Mission Training

Queen's University

Kingston, ON

Bachelor of Science Honours - Physics Major, Computing Minor

2013 - 2018

Experience

Queen's Space Engineering Team - Satellite Project

Kingston, ON

Chief Technical Officer

September 2019 - Present

- Manages and supports a team of 50+ students which designs and constructs a 3U cube satellite.
- Hired project managers for the major satellite subsystems.

Docupet Inc

Kingston, ON

Junior Web Developer

October 2018 - Present

- Responsible for large data set analysis and ETL using Python and MySQL.
- Developing Docupet Import Module using Django.

Royal Military College of Canada - Physics & Space Science Department

Kingston, ON

Observatory/Teaching Assistant

September 2018 - Present

- Trained students on reflector telescope usage for undergraduate astronomy courses.
- Guided student astronomical observing sessions.

Alma Mater Society of Queen's University Inc

Kingston, ON

Director of Information Technology

March 2017 - May 2018

- Member of the AMS Board of Directors, responsible for corporation-wide strategic planning.
- Maintained the technological infrastructure, performed account management, and oversaw project development.
- Trained and managed first level IT support staff.

Queen's Space Engineering Team - Satellite Project

Kingston, ON

May 2017 - May 2019

- Electrical Systems Design Lead
 - Designed and implemented the power generation and delivery system for CoSMOSat.
 - Managed the periphery electrical subsystems, including command/data-handling, and attitude determination.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON May 2016 - April 2017

Electrical Projects Director

- Delegated and monitored projects in data collection, energy storage, and low power home electricity usage.
- Designed and installed a fully off-grid photovoltaic power generation system for a 600sqft home.

Queen's Solar Design Team

Kingston, ON

Data Systems Manager

September 2015 - April 2016

- Designed and installed weather and data monitoring systems for the Queen's Solar Education Centre.
- Includes hardware implementation throughout the home as well as software development.

Various Part-time work

Kingston, ON

Roles in service industry, education, and university athletics

2014-2018

Projects

Polar Dust Loading Analysis using MetOp-A AVHRR Imagery

Master's of Physics and Space Science Thesis Project

Royal Military College of Canada May 2019 - Present

- Aims to produce a large time scale dataset of new high latitude climate markers and determine, if applicable, what insights can be gained through statistical analysis with contemporary polar climate data.
- Studies the impact of dust aerosols on polar amplification models and the disappearing cryosphere.
- Utilizes Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) imagery and novel distributed computing techniques to perform mass trend analysis.

Space Mission Design & Analysis

NSERC CREATE International Space Mission Training

Royal Military College of Canada

- January 2019 July 2019
- Collaborated with international colleagues to design a 3U cubesat mission to study polar mesospheric clouds using an infrared spectrometer
- Worked with a team of students from the University of Tromsø and the University of Saskatchewan to design and construct a a weather balloon mission to study ionizing radiation at high altitudes.

NGVS Surface Brightness Profile Fitting

Queen's University

Honours Physics Thesis Project

September 2017 - May 2018

- Study the light profile of Virgo Cluster galaxies to detect the trace of stellar halos.
- Use of chi-squared and Markov Chain Monte Carlo minimization techniques to determine the light percentage contributed by halo stars.

Investigating Hydrodynamic Quantum Analogues

Queen's University

Physics Laboratory, PHYS 350

December 2016 - May 2017

- By mechanically vibrating viscous fluids, several quantum mechanical effects can be demonstrated.

Implementation of Kalman Filters for Apogee Detection in Rocket Flight

Queen's University

Queen's Rocket Engineering Team

September 2016 - January 2017

- Research into the viability of using a Kalman filter to deploy airbrakes on atmospheric rocket flight.
- Implementation of algorithm using an Arduino platform with pressure altimeter and 9-axis accelerometer.

Determining the Width of the Kirkwood Gaps

Queen's University

Computational Methods in Physics, PHYS 313

September 2015 - December 2015

- Wrote a limited N-body code (in C) to simulate the motion of asteroids in resonance with Jupiter and Saturn.
- Co-wrote scientific report detailing the findings and results of the Verlet simulation.

Skills Profile

Technologies Skills

Programming: Proficient in Python Space mission design

Experience in C, MATLAB, Java Web: Proficient in Django, Bootstrap, Symfony Astrodynamics and Orbital Mechanics

Experience in JS/HTML/CSS/PHP/MySQL

Typesetting in LATEX Software:

Volunteer and team management Space simulation in AGI STK

> PCB design in KiCAD/Eagle Agile development and Git version control

Graphic design in Inkscape/GIMP/Visio 3D design in SOLIDWORKS Scientific computing and ETL processes

Certifications and Courses

Amateur Radio Operator (callsign: VE3KSP)

Innovation, Science, and Economic Development Canada

Graduate Professional Skills Certificate

University of Saskatoon

February 2017 Saskatoon, SK August 2019

Toronto, ON

References

Dr. Ron Vincent

Professor of Physics

Andrew Comber

Chief Technology Officer

Dr. Stéphane Courteau

Professor of Astronomy

Royal Military College of Canada Master's thesis supervisor

> Docupet Inc. Direct supervisor

Queen's University

Undergraduate thesis supervisor